Guide to the Jacob Leslie Crane papers, 1927-1980, 1946-1965 (bulk)
Crane, Jacob Leslie papers,
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Jacob Leslie Crane papers, 1927-1980 1946-1965 (bulk)
2646
Jacob L. (Jacob Leslie) Crane, 1892-1988
3.5 cubic ft.
Correspondence, accounts, drafts, reports, and working and reference papers such as maps, charts, and legislation.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Seven project files composed largely of correspondence, accounts, drafts, reports, and working and reference papers such as maps, charts, and legislation relating to city planning. Also, printed material by Crane, and correspondence with Constantine Doxiadis. Files contain projects for the United Nations, 1946-1955; Greece, 1950-1956; Puerto Rico, 1952-1962; Piney Orchard, Maryland, 1954-1958; Norfolk, Virginia, 1954-1965; Baltimore, Maryland, 1955-1956; and Ponca City, Oklahoma, 1927, 1955-1959.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Jacob Leslie Crane was born in 1892 in Benzonia, Michigan. He received a degree in civil engineering from the University of Michigan and a planning degree from Harvard in 1921, where he studied under John Nolen. Crane worked as a consultant in the United States and 25 other countries, preparing 60 zoning plans and ordinances, and acting as an expert witness in zoning cases. He served as a consultant to many government agencies, including the Tennessee Valley Authority, National Resources Planning Board, Federal Housing Administration, United States Housing Authority, Defense Housing, Housing and Home Finance Agency, and the Division of Urban Development of the National Housing Agency. He was also consultant to the Canal Zone and the Republic of Panama, 1944; member and president of the American Institute of Planners; consultant for the United Nations Department of Social Affairs, Housing and Planning Section, and the United Nations Technical Assistance Administration; and consultant to many other U.N. projects.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
The papers of Jacob Crane, consisting of seven project files, give only brief vignettes of a long career in planning and relate chiefly to Crane's work as a consultant. While still in the federal civil service as assistant to the Administrator of Housing and Home Finance Agency in international affairs, he served as consultant to Puerto Rico and to the United Nations Department of Social Affairs. His consulting work represented in his papers includes studies in housing, new towns, a master plan, urban renewal, and rehabilitation studies. Also worth noting is Crane's 1933 Iowa Twenty-Year Conservation Plan, an early example of state planning, a printed copy of which is in Mann Library.
Crane was acquainted with Constantine Doxiadis and became a senior consultant for Doxiadis Associates, an international firm, in 1955. There is correspondence with Doxiadis under two projects--Greece and Ponca City, Oklahoma--which contains an interested memorandum outlining Doxiadis' procedure for a study.
The collection is divided into seven subject files, arranged chronologically by the commencement date of the project. The material is largely correspondence, accounts revealing the locale and duration of employ, drafts and reports, and some working and reference papers such as maps, charts, legislation, etc.
There is a small quantity of printed material by Crane, transferred from other collections.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Crane, Jacob L. (Jacob Leslie), 1892-1988.; Doxiadis, Constantine.; United Nations.
Subjects:
City planning.; City planning--Greece.; City planning--Puerto Rico.; Civil engineers.; City planners.
Places:
Piney Orchard (Md.)--City planning.; Baltimore (Md.)--City planning.; Norfolk (Va.)--City planning.; Ponca City (Okla.)--City planning.
Form and Genre Terms:
Maps.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. United Nations, 1946-1955
Box 1
Series II. Greece, 1950-1956
Boxes 1, 3
Series III. Puerto Rico, 1952-1962
Boxes 2, 4
Series IV. Piney Orchard, Maryland, 1954-1958
Box 2
Series V. Norfolk, Virginia, 1954-1965
Box 3
Series VI. Baltimore, Maryland, 1955-1956
Box 3
Series VII. Ponca City, Oklahoma, 1927, 1955-1959
Box 3
Series VIII. Printed material
Boxes 3, 4
Series IX. Other
Box 4
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. United Nations, 1946-1955
  Crane held various appointments as housing consultant for the U.N. Department of Social Affairs, Housing and Planning Section, and for the U.N. Technical Assistance Administration. H.H.F.A. granted him leave for this work. November 13, 1950-January 26, 1951, he was chairman of the U.N. Mission to S.E. Asia on tropical housing. 1951 he prepared his report "Study on Methods of Preparing Programs of National Governments for Housing and Community Development," stressing methodology. He was seminar advisor for the U.N. Regional Seminar on Housing and Community Development, January 21, 1953-February 17, 1953, in New Delhi and produced the paper "Experience of National Government in Preparing Programmes for Housing and Community Development." In 1955 Crane did a study on demographic information needed for planning housing program in Economic Commisssion for Asia and Far East region to be used at Rio De Janeiro Seminar. This was under the joint auspices of U.N. Technical Assistance Divison and International Social Science Council.
  - United Nations - Correspondence and accounts, 1946-1954 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    Correspondence of Ernest Wiessman, U.N. Department of Social Affairs-Housing and Planning Section, U.N. Technical Assistance Administration
  - United Nations - Correspondence and reports, 1951-1953 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
    Correspondence with Roy J. Boroughs, Ernest Weissman, Einer Engberg, United Nations. Department of Social Affairs. Housing and Planning Section, U.S. Housing and Home Finance Agency, International Housing Activities
  - United Nations - Correspondence and report, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Correspondence with Eleanor Hinder, United Nations. Technical Assistance Administration
  - United Nations - Correspondence and report, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Correspondence with Donald Young, John Durand, Anatole Solow, United Nations. Bureau of Social Affairs-Director in charge of population, International Social Science Council, Organization of American States. Division of Housing and Town Planning
- Series II. Greece, 1950-1956
  In 1954 Constantine Doxiadis renewed aquaintences with Crane and interested him in making a report for the National Mortgage Bank of Greece on proposed housing policy, especially the financial and technical aspects. Crane was engaged by the Bank in August 1954, and according to his scheduling studied the Greek situation by reports from Greece, U.N., and U.S. agencies, then visited Greece for a field trip in March 1955-April 1955. In May 1955 he presented his report, "National Housing Policy in Greece," advocating the building of a Home Loan Savings Bank type program around the National Mortgage Bank. Renewed contacts with Doxiadis led to Crane becoming a senior consultant for Doxiadis Associates.
  - Greece - Correspondence, 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Correspondence with Constantine Doxiadis, Charles C. Arliotis, National Mortgage Bank of Greece, International Bank for Reconstruction and Development, Housing and Home Finance Agency. International Housing Section
  - Greece - Studies and reports, 1950-1954 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Studies and reports by Roy Burroughs, George Speer, Jan Bommer, Yves Salaun, U.N. Economic Commission for Europe, U.N. Department of Social Affairs-Housing and Planning Section, U.S. Economic Cooperative Administration Mission in Greece, International Confederation of Free Trade Unions, National Mortgage Bank of Greece
  - Greece - Notes, draft of report, ca. 1955 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Correspondence with the National Mortgage Bank of Greece
  - Greece - Report, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Reports
    - National housing policy in Greece. (typescript). Crane, Jacob, May 1955 (Box 1)
    - Post War Housing in Greece...Greek State ECA accomplishments in attacking the post war housing problem. (multi-copied) Speer, George A., March 1, 1951 (Box 1)
    - The Greek Housing Situation Report. Athens, U.S.A. Operations Missions to Greece. Jenks, Barton P., June 1957 (Box 1)
    - Destruction of towns and villages in Greece. Athens. Ministry of Reconstruction publication #11 - Inscription to Crane from head of Housing Dept. Doxiadis, Constantine, 1947 (Box 1)
    - Economic policy for the reconstruction of the settlement of Greece. Under-secretary for the Reconstruction publication #3 - Inscription to Crane from head of Housing Dept. Doxiadis, Constantine A., ca. 1946 (Box 1)
    - Greece...Experimental settlement of St. George Keratasine. Piraeus. Athens. Dept. of Reconstruction report C1 - Part of report by Doxiadis. Department of Reconstruction, 1947 (Box 1)
    - The Greek House. Its Evolution and its Relation to the House of other Blakan Peoples. Athens. Ministry of Reconstruction publication #37. Megas, George A., 1951 (Box 1)
    - Annual Report, National Mortgage Bank of Greece, 1953, 1955 (Box 1)
    - Savings and loan associations, their services, National Savings and Loan League, 1952 (Box 1)
    - Rules and regulations for insurance of accounts,. Federal Savings and Loan Insurance Corporation, Washington D.C. Federal Home Loan Bank Board, September 1, 1953 (Box 1)
    - Federal Savings and Loan Associations. What they are...and how charters are granted, Federal Home Loan Bank Board, February 1955 (Box 1)
    - Rules and regulations for the Federal Savings and Loan System. With amendments to April 15, 1954. (2 copies) Federal Home Loan and Bank Board, April 15, 1954 (Box 1)
    - Federal Home Loan Bank Act. Provisions of Home Owners' Loan Act of 1933...as amended to January 1, 1952. Washington, H.H.F.A. (2 copies) Housing and Home Finance Agency, Federal Home Loan Bank Board, January 1, 1952 (Box 1)
- Series III. Puerto Rico, 1952-1962
  Crane held a number of consulting jobs of short duration mostly with Puerto Rican government agencies and Puerto Rican Industrial Development Companies. He consulted on planning and housing matters (public housing, low cost private housing, cooperative housing), creation of the Housing Research Board to replace the Model Housing Board, an establishment of Commonwealth States for Puerto Rico, financing of mortgages, etc. Papers include his reports of August 11, 1955, March 9, 1956, March 1957, and July 30, 1960. An interesting series of reports by George Reed, Consultant FOA describes history and issues of housing since 1934 in Puerto Rico.
  - Puerto Rico - Correspondence, 1952-1962, undated (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
    Correspondence with Ramon Avila Sanchez, Luis Rivera Santos, George L. Reed, Housing Research Board, Puerto Rico Urban Renewal and Housing Corporation
  - Puerto Rico Accounts - Income tax returns, contracts, accounts, 1956-1962 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Correspondence with Managment Services, Administration for Cooperative Development, Puerto Rico Industrial Development Company
  - Puerto Rico - Reports (multi-copied), 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Correspondence with George Reed, Consultant
  - Puerto Rico - Legislation (multi-copied), 1934, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Correspondence with U.S. Congress, Puerto Rico
  - Puerto Rico - Reports, multi-copied, typescript, Spanish and English, 1955-1960 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Puerto Rico - Article, bulletin, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Puerto Rico - Newspaper clippings, advertisements, in Spanish., 1954-1956 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Aided self-help material, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Reports
    - "A report on the renewal possibilities of the historic triangle of the city of San Juan." Keith, Nathaniel, May 1955 (Box 2)
    - "First annual report" (typescript) Puerto Rico Housing Research Board, 1954-1955 (Box 2)
    - "Housing problems and policies of Commonwealth of Puerto Rico" (multi-copied) Puerto Rico. Puerto Rico Housing Authority, December 16, 1955 (Box 2)
- Series IV. Piney Orchard, Maryland, 1954-1958
  Crane and Elbert Peets were hired as consultants by Winwood Corporation (owned by National Plastics) to plan and lay out a new model town of 900 single family houses and 200 garden apartments between Baltimore and Washington D.C. near Fort Meade. Country Manor Estaes Corp. of Foundation Co-operative Housing Inc., the National Security Agency group, was interested in developing an housing area but the project foundered over provisions of water and sewage facilities and F.H.A. requirements.
  - Piney orchard, Maryland - Correspondence, 1954-1958, undated (Box 2, Folder 13-16)
    Correspondence with David T. Raisen, Ephraim Winer, E.V. Bueneman, Roger Willcox, Philip Klutznick, Winwood Corp., Country Manor Estates Corp., Foundation for Cooperative Housing, Inc.
  - Piney Orchard, Maryland - Plans, drawings, specifications, ca. (approximately), 1955 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Correspondence with Charles Wagner, Winwood Corp.
- Series V. Norfolk, Virginia, 1954-1965
  Correspondence with Lawrence Cox, Norfolk Redevelopment and Housing Authority and with S.E. Virginia Regional Planning and Economic Developemnt Commission about planning and possible consultation; correpondence on Advisory Plan for selecting developer for Hauge Residential Site Development.
  - Norfolk - Correspondence, 1954-1962 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Correspondence with Lawrence Cox, Wendell Winn, Norfolk Redevelopment and Housing Authority, S.E. Virginia Regional Planning, Economic Development Commission
  - Norfolk. Norfolk Redevelopment and Housing Authority. Hague Residential Site Redevelopment - Correspondence, 1962-1965 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Correspondence with Lawrence Cox
  - Norfolk - Clippings, notes, 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Correspondence with Hilltop Enterprises
  - Norfolk. Norfolk Redevelopment and Housing Authority. Hague Residential Site Redevelopment - Farms, invitation to bid, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Norfolk - Maps and plans, charts, 1954-1961 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Reports and Legislation
    - Virginia. Department of Conservation and Economic Development. Planning Legislation. (multi-copied), 1958 (Box 3)
    - Southeastern Virginia Regional Planning Commission By-laws (as amended August 14, 1958). (multi-copied), 1958 (Box 3)
    - A master plan for the central business and financial district. (multi-copied) Agle, Charles, July 1956 (Box 3)
- Series VI. Baltimore, 1955-1956
  Crane was consultant in 1955-1956 when Baltimore Urban Renewal and Housing Agency was established for urban renewal projects; typical deteriorated block in Harlem Park created "314" pilot study for rehabilitation.
  - Baltimore - Correspondence, 1955-1956 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Correspondence with Jacob Crane, Oliver Winston, Eugene Wheeler, Baltimore Planning Department, Office of Urban Renewal Coordinator
  - Baltimore "314" Rehabilitation Project Harlem Park - Correspondence, reports, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Correspondence with Eugene Wheeler, R.L. Steiner, Philip Darling, Baltimore Planning Department, Urban Renewal Administration, H.H.F.A.
  - Baltimore - News releases, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Correspondence with Housing and Home Finance Agency
  - Baltimore - Newspaper clippings, 1954-1956 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Baltimore - Report (multi-copied), 1956 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Correspondence with Urban Renewal Staff Committee Report
  - Baltimore - Draft report, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Correspondence with Urban Renewal Advisory Council
  - Reports
    - Report to Mayor Thomas d'Alesandro Jr.,. Appendices. Baltimore. Urban Renewal Study Board, September 1956 (Box 3)
    - Baltimore city zoning ordinances and state enabling act. Baltimore. Planning Commission, 1956 (Box 3)
    - Maryland zoning and planning enabling act. Published by Women's Civic League. Charlottesville, Virginia Maryland, 1956 (Box 3)
    - Study of the attitudes of potential applicants toward public housing. (multi-copied) Baltimore Housing Authority, January 1954 (Box 3)
    - Workable program for urban renewal in Baltimore, Maryland. (multi-copied) Baltimore. City Council, November 22, 1954 (Box 3)
    - Housing rehabilitation and enforcement of housing laws. Public health monograph no. 34 U.S. Department of Health, Education and Welfare. Public Health Service, Undated (Box 3)
    - The legal basis for redevelopment in Baltimore, Maryland. (multi-copied) Baltimore. Redevelopment Commission, September 1949 (Box 3)
- Series VII. Ponca City, Oklahoma; 1927, 1955-1959
  Crane prepared first master plan, 1927; hired as consultant for two two year terms, 1955-1957, 1957-1959; supervised hiring planner, applying for "701" H.H.F.A. grant for planning studies, tentative approaches to urban renewal grant for Dixie Hill, brought Doxiadis Inc. for an urban renewal and civic facilities study, 1959.
  - Ponca City, Oklahoma - Correspondence; 1955-1959, Undated (Box 3, Folder 12-16)
    Correspondence with Frank Winsted, Joe Hutchison, Marvin Hatcher, Constantine Doxiadis
  - Ponca City, Oklahoma - Newspaper clippings, 1955-1957, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Ponca City, Oklahoma - Leaflets, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Ponca City, Oklahoma - Pamphlet, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Correspondence with State of Oklahoma
  - Ponca City, Oklahoma - Pamphlets (multi-copied), 1957 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Correspondence with Ponca City, Oklahoma
  - Ponca City, Oklahoma - Maps, subdivision plans, 1955-1959 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Reports
    - The Development Plans of Ponca City, Oklahoma, annotated Crane, Jacob, 1927 (Box 3)
    - Urban renewal possibilities, development of Lake Ponca and a civil facilities program for Ponca City, Oklahoma. Under a contract with the Department of Commerce. Industry State of Oklahoma. Winter, Doxiadis, Associates Inc., 1959 (Box 3)
- Series VIII. Printed material
  - "City Planning in the Soviet Union" in the Economic Review of the Soviet Union Crane, Jacob, January 15, 1932 (Box 3)
  - Report on the Iowa Twenty-five Year Conservation Plan. Prepared for the Iowa Board of Conservation and the Iowa Fish and Game Commission. Des Moins, Iowa, Wallace-Homestead Co. Transferred to Mann Library, New York State School of Agriculture, Cornell. Crane, Jacob, 1933 (Box 3)
  - "Making Cities out of Housing Programs." Outline of Address before Annual Meeting, National Association of Housing Officials, New York City Crane, Jacob, May 20, 1943 (Box 3)
  - Urban Planning - Illusion and Reality: A New Philosophy for Planned City Building. New York: Vantage Press, 169 pp. Autographed first edition presented to Arthur Bohnen, May 1973. Rec'd. from Arthur Bohnen, 1976 but not accessioned, per. H. Finch. Crane, Jacob L., 1973 (Box 3)
  - Misc. journals, 1942-1953 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Additional material by Jacob Crane (Box 4, Folder 5-7)
- Series IX. Other
  - Preliminary Report on Federal Aid to Urban Land Acquisition, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Report to the Bureau of Indian Affairs, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 4)